A Guide to the Milton LaTour Grigg Papers, 1930-1981
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Milton LaTour Grigg Papers 1930-1981
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
6478-a
This collection consists of ca. 1,800 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The Grigg Papers were a gift to the Library from Mrs. Milton L. Grigg of Charlottesville, Virginia, through Mr. K. Edward Lay, Jr., University of Virginia School of Architecture, on December 6, 1983.
Biographical/Historical Information
Milton LaTour Grigg was born on April 18, 1905, in Alexandria, Virginia, the son of Jams Fossett and Mary Emily (Glascor) Grigg. He graduated from Alexandria High School in 1924 and attended the University of Virginia as a special student in the Department of Engineering and School of Architecture from 1924 to 1929.
After completing his studies, he was employed by the architectural firm of Perry, Shaw and Hepburn, Boston, Massachusetts, as a draftsman and designer for the restoration of Colonial Williamsburg. In 1933, Grigg started his private practice in Charlottesville, and eventually established an office in Alexandria; he became a senor partner in the firm of Grigg, Wood, and Browne. Grigg's firm specialized in churches, estates, and restoration. He served as the Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation's architect and supervised the 1953 restoratoin of "Monticello." Grigg was responsible for the design of the U.S. Embassy in Canberra, Australia, and the notable St. John's Lutheran Church, Emporia, Virginia; and was a medallist in a competition sponsored by Better Homes in America.
During 1942-1945, Grigg served as the civilian head of the Design Section for the Army Corps of Engineers in Washington, chiefly designing military hospitals and other structures. He also served on commissions and boards in the city of Charlottesville; these included the Planning Commission, the Building Code Commission, aht the Building Code Appeal Board. He was also a member of the Rotary Club.
Grigg was a fellow of the American Institute of Architects (three-time president of the Virginia chapter), and also served as its director for the Middle Atlantic Region. He was twice president of the Church Architectural Guild of America, 1963-1964; president of the Interfaith Research Center in New York, and a comptroller of the International Congress on Religious Architecture.
Grigg died on March 23, 1982, aged seventy-six.
Scope and Content Information
This collection contains ca. 1,800 items (4 Hollinger boxes, ca. 1.5 linear feet), ca. 1930-1981, papers of Milton LaTour Girgg, a Charlottesville, Virginia, architect. It consists primarily of newsclippings from various newspapers and periodicals about Grigg's projects and designs, including the 1953 restoration of "Monticello." There are a large number of bulletins from various churches he designed or restored. The collection also includes letters, photographs, printed material, and memorabilia.
The newsclippings and church bulletins provide information on Grigg-designed churches as publicized by news media and their respective congregations. Other newsclippings pertain to his designs for residential, public, and commercial buildings. Also included among the newsclippings are articles regarding his involvement in professional organizations.
The collection encompasses his fifty-year career as an architect, beginning with his involvement in the restoration of Colonial Williamsburg, Virginia.
Arrangement
Folder Heading have been preserved with some modifications; the folders are arranged alphabetically.
Contents List
- Alexandria 1945-1966 (Box 1)
- Awards 1934-1980; n.d. (Box 1)
- Bulletins from Grigg-Designed Churches 1945-1974, 4 folders (Box 1)
- Bulletins from Grigg-Designed Churches 1975-1980; n.d., 2 folders (Box 2)
- Charleston, South Carolina 1977-1980; n.d. (Box 2)
- Charlottesville, Virginia 1947-1980 (Box 2)
- Churches: Miscellaneous Material Re Grigg 1949-1969 (Box 2)
- Falls Church, Virginia 1953-1958 (Box 2)
- Gadsby Tavern 1933-1966 (Box 2)
- Grigg Church Designs: Newsclippings 1947-1962, 2 folders (Box 2)
- Grigg Church Designs: Newsclippings 1960-1981; n.d., 2 folders (Box 3)
- Grigg House Designs: Newsclippings 1934-1979; n.d. (Box 3)
- Grigg Projects: Miscellaneous Newsclippings 1951-1980; n.d. (Box 3)
- Illustrations and Related Items 1931-1979; n.d. (Box 3)
- Letters and Related Items 1931-1981 (Box 3)
- "Monticello" Clippings 1938-1971; n.d. (Box 3)
- Newsclippings and Printed Material 1930-1981; n.d., 3 folders (Box 4)
- Photographs 1932-1977; n.d., 2 folders (Box 4)
- Ramsey House 1946-1956; n.d. (Box 4)
- Thomas Jefferson Inn 1950-1978; n.d. (Box 4)